<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the Chappel Royal in the Tower, upon Sunday the sixth day of January, 1694/5, being the feast of the Epiphany as also the day whereon the greatest part of that audience  appeared in deep mourning, upon the death of Her Sacred Majesty, our late gracious Queen Mary / by John Finglas ...</title>
            <author>Finglas, John, Prebend of St. Audoens, Dublin.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85305</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">38876072</idno>
  <idno type="VID">152267</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240871713</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F951A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42987</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">38876072</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85305)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152267)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2289:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the Chappel Royal in the Tower, upon Sunday the sixth day of January, 1694/5, being the feast of the Epiphany as also the day whereon the greatest part of that audience  appeared in deep mourning, upon the death of Her Sacred Majesty, our late gracious Queen Mary / by John Finglas ...</title>
                  <author>Finglas, John, Prebend of St. Audoens, Dublin.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the Author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Includes marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Lambeth Palace Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Mary --  II, --  Queen of England, 1662-1694.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152267:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at the Chappel Royal IN THE TOWER, UPON Sunday the Sixth Day of <hi>January,</hi> 1694/5.</p>
            <p>BEING THE <hi>Feast of the Epiphany:</hi> AS ALSO, The Day whereon the greatest part of that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience appeared in Deep Mourning, upon the Death of Her SACRED MAJESTY, Our Late Gracious QUEEN <hi>MARY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN FINGLAS,</hi> Prebendary of St. <hi>Audoens Dublin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:152267:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:152267:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable ROBERT Lord <hi>Lucas,</hi> Baron of <hi>Shenfield,</hi> Chief Governour of His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> and Lord Lieutenant of the <hi>Hamlets</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto belonging.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Noble LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>'TWill be no Compliment, <hi>in</hi> any <hi>Sense,</hi> to tell Your Lordship, that, as You did not easily perswade me into the <hi>Pulpit;</hi> so, nothing less than Your Commands, should (at this time) have forced me to the <hi>Press.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am here a <hi>Stranger,</hi> under all the disad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages that may be, for Study; and not only
<pb facs="tcp:152267:3"/> so, but my <hi>Thoughts</hi> at present, more ruffled and disturb'd than ever.</p>
            <p>As 'twas my misfortune to have but very few Friends <hi>here,</hi> so, 'twas my happiness, that they were <hi>the</hi> Best and greatest that <hi>England</hi> could afford: Her late <hi>MAJESTY</hi> of <hi>Bles<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed Memory;</hi> and His <hi>Grace,</hi> the <hi>Late Lord Arch-Bishop of CANTERBURY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Affair I came to manage, being a Service to the <hi>Church,</hi> an endeavour to remove a most Perfidious incroachment on her <hi>Rights;</hi> recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended me to Their Favour; and the Design ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared to be so Just, and so much for the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick</hi> Good; <hi>that,</hi> as his <hi>Grace,</hi> upon the first no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, was pleased heartily to espouse it: So, when it was (in His <hi>MAJESTIES</hi> absence) proposed to the <hi>QUEEN;</hi> it gained Her approbation so far; that with a great, but <hi>Sweet Condiscension,</hi> She was pleased to say, <hi>She would become my So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitress Her self.</hi> But, <hi>Alas!</hi> All this now, serves only to agravate my sorrow, and heighten
<pb facs="tcp:152267:3"/> my loss, which is more than ordinary, and every way great, not only in <hi>Common,</hi> as a <hi>Subject,</hi> not only in a more particular Relation, as a <hi>Church-man</hi> (tho' the meanest of all) but, in my, <hi>Yet more private</hi> Circumstances; having at a great expence of time and Charge, brought this Matter to be fit for a Royal Decision, and, all of a sudden, deprived of <hi>Those, who</hi> were gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciously pleased to Patronize both me and it. And tho' I have this Comfort; that, as that God, who hath called Her <hi>MAJESTY</hi> to an <hi>Incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible Crown,</hi> hath left us her <hi>other Self</hi> (whom God long continue to us, and over us) from whom I may hope for all due Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: So, his <hi>Grace</hi> is Succeeded by that <hi>Person,</hi> of the <hi>Age,</hi> who is most Eminent for such Services.</p>
            <p>But <hi>Yet,</hi> notwithstanding these <hi>Abatements,</hi> I cannot easily extricate my self, from the Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize and Amazement that so justly seized me; and 'tis <hi>well,</hi> if the effects thereof, do not too visibly appear in the following Discourse.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:152267:4"/>
            <p>But I know 'twas not Your <hi>Lordships</hi> Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of my performance, but Your Zeal for the <hi>Subject,</hi> together with the joynt desires of <hi>Some,</hi> whose importunity I resisted, that made You resolve (against all that I could offer to the contrary) to have it Published. You re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, it had given You some faint <hi>Idea's</hi> of Your <hi>Dear,</hi> tho' <hi>Dead Mistriss;</hi> and contain'd some Motives (<hi>the best</hi> I could think of, with relation to the subject, and as <hi>Many</hi> as the time would allow) to promote the Service of Your <hi>Royal Master, wherein</hi> (I can bear Your <hi>Lordship</hi> witness) You would think the last drop of Your <hi>Blood</hi> well spent.</p>
            <p>May Your <hi>Loyal</hi> Example have its due in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon others, and convince, even those un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reasonable (shall I call them?) <hi>Men</hi> among us, who are so strangely insatuated, as to act every way, as much against their <hi>Interest,</hi> as their <hi>Duty.</hi> And if any thing I have said here, to which (tho' I now find it swelled beyond the
<pb facs="tcp:152267:4"/> ordinary bulk of a Sermon) I have not added a Syllable, but omitted much of what I deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, may contribute to the same end. I shall have all I desire, and all I design, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides the satisfaction of giving Your <hi>Lordship</hi> a full proof of my Obedience, and thereby mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festing, how much, I am, in all <hi>Sincerity,</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
               <signed>Your Lordships Most Humble Servant, JOHN FINGLAS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:152267:5"/>
            <p>THere has happen'd some small Mistakes at the <hi>Press,</hi> especially in the Pointing, which the <hi>Reader</hi> is desired to consider, and help with his Pen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:152267:5"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>ISAIAH XL. 6, 7, 8.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The Voice said, Cry. And he said, What shall I cry? All flesh is grass, and all the goodliness thereof is as the flower of the field.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The grass withereth, the flower fadeth, because the spirit of the Lord hath blown upon it: surely the people is grass.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The grass withereth, the flower fadeth: but the word of our God shall stand for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>I QUESTION not, but upon the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Text,</hi> you easily observ'd it, to suit but too well with the <hi>sad</hi> and bewailed occasion of this <hi>days</hi> Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; which hath given us (beyond any thing to <hi>us</hi> known) a doleful Instance of its Truth; and all I can say, will come infinitely short of the <hi>sad</hi> but <hi>clear</hi> Comment, which <hi>the Breath</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lam. 4. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
               <hi>of our Nostrils,</hi> She of whom we said, <hi>Nations shall rest under her shadow;</hi> hath given us upon <hi>it,</hi> who being <hi>dead</hi> yet speaks, yea <hi>crys,</hi> in a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152267:6"/>
               <hi>lowder</hi> than the Prophets <hi>Voice, All flesh is grass,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All flesh.</hi> It pleased the great <hi>Creator</hi> of all things to make at first Three Sorts of Living Creatures; <hi>Angels</hi> he made pure <hi>spirits</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>flesh,</hi> and therefore, only for <hi>Heaven,</hi> not to dwell on <hi>Earth. Brutes</hi> he made <hi>flesh,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>immortal souls,</hi> and therefore, only for <hi>Earth,</hi> not to pretend to <hi>Heaven. Man</hi> is of a middle Nature, partaking both of <hi>flesh</hi> and <hi>spirit;</hi> and therefore made both for Heaven and Earth. But as his <hi>flesh</hi> is but to minister and serve his <hi>spirit,</hi> so he was made for <hi>Earth,</hi> but as his pas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage and way to <hi>Heaven,</hi> not, that this should he his <hi>home</hi> or <hi>happiness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BUT, how wofully have we perverted this Order, whose incessant cares for the things of <hi>this life,</hi> sufficiently declare, that we believe our selves <hi>here</hi> at home? <hi>One</hi> man eagerly pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing sensual pleasures, as if he had nothing to mind, or hope for, but what the <hi>beasts</hi> enjoy. <hi>Another,</hi> Riches, and that with so much earnest<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, as if he were to enjoy the same for ever; tho' the <hi>fool</hi> knows not but this very <hi>night</hi> he must part from them. A <hi>third</hi> hunting after <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> and <hi>dominion;</hi> so, as to stick at nothing that may compass it, and yet little knows, how soon his <hi>Honour</hi> may be laid in the dust. A
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152267:6"/>
               <hi>fourth</hi> after popular applause, which is nothing but a <hi>blast,</hi> nothing more vain and uncertain than <hi>it</hi> is. <hi>Whereas,</hi> if we did but rightly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstand our <hi>state</hi> and <hi>condition here,</hi> and serious<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly consider, that <hi>all flesh is grass,</hi> we would little value <hi>these</hi> things, and at best, <hi>use the World, as if we us'd it not; Ʋse</hi> it, no otherwise than a traveller doth his <hi>Inn;</hi> and how is that? when he comes there, tho' he finds every thing <hi>ready,</hi> a <hi>room</hi> well furnish'd, and all things therein, not only conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient but delightful too; yet he is not so <hi>silly</hi> as to <hi>set</hi> his <hi>heart upon them;</hi> because he knows, on the <hi>morrow</hi> he is to leave them and be gone; and, there's no Man that travels home-ward, that would multiply businesses on himself <hi>unnecessari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> in the way. When he is at <hi>home,</hi> in his <hi>house,</hi> he may find sundry imployments to busie him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self about, but in the <hi>Inn</hi> he cares for nothing, but <hi>rest</hi> and <hi>refreshment; so,</hi> men that are thoughtful, or wise, know themselves to be but <hi>strangers and Pilgrims</hi> here; and therefore look<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 11.</note> for a <hi>Countrey</hi> and <hi>City</hi> to come; and so think it no wisdom, to intermeddle too much in the affairs of that <hi>Countrey,</hi> through which only they are to pass; but as <hi>Citizens</hi> of <hi>Heaven</hi> send up their hearts desire, where they profess their <hi>treasure is.</hi> This <hi>Lesson</hi> our Saviour teacheth, when he tells us, <hi>After all these things below do</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat 6. 31, 32.</note>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:152267:7"/>
               <hi>the Gentiles seek,</hi> but <hi>seek ye the kingdom of God, and the righteousness of it.</hi> And St. <hi>Paul</hi> assures, us, <hi>the fashion of this world passeth away;</hi> and<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 31.</note> wisheth <hi>us</hi> not to <hi>fashion</hi> our selves to it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Could</hi> a Traveller justly <hi>Seize</hi> all the valuable things that occur in his <hi>way,</hi> and convey them to his <hi>home,</hi> so as to be of advantage to him <hi>there;</hi> his endeavouring it, might be the more excusable. <hi>And</hi> so, in our <hi>case,</hi> could a <hi>man</hi> carry the <hi>World</hi> to <hi>Hell,</hi> to bribe the flames, or corrupt his tormentors, there were something to be said for our <hi>fondness</hi> of it; but the Psalmist hath already assur'd us of the contrary, <hi>His</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 49. 17.</note>
               <hi>glory shall not descend after him.</hi> Or could he (tho at the expence of all his worldly injoyments) buy out his pardon, or procure his peace, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he come <hi>there;</hi> This might well excuse our grasping at <hi>it:</hi> but that's not to be done, neither, for <hi>the redemption of the soul is precious,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 8</note>
               <hi>and ceaseth for ever: And what shall a man give</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 16. 26</note>
               <hi>in exchange for his soul? For</hi> what <hi>material</hi> thing can equalize a <hi>Spirit?</hi> Many things may be had, more precious and fine than the <hi>Body,</hi> but all of them have no proportion to a Spiritual Being. St. <hi>Paul,</hi> we know, counts all things but <hi>dung;</hi> and can we think that God will take<note place="margin">Phil. 3. 8.</note> dung in Exchange for a Soul? O! how dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful will it be at last, to think, that for a little of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152267:7"/> the <hi>world,</hi> for the satisfaction of a <hi>lust,</hi> for a few drossie pleasures, and sensual delights, which have been here (not without the mixture of much <hi>sorrow</hi> and <hi>allay</hi> injoyed) you have lost your <hi>souls,</hi> and forfeited your interest in those <hi>Mansions</hi> that are <hi>above,</hi> where <hi>there are pleasures for evermore:</hi> and all this (in a great measure) because we believe not, at least, mind not this <hi>Voice</hi> in the Text, <hi>All flesh is grass.</hi> And what more withering and fading? <hi>Dust</hi> it is, and<note place="margin">Gen. 18. 27. 1 Cor. 15. 42.</note> what baser? <hi>Corruption</hi> it is, and what viler? And yet, was the <hi>Son</hi> of God himself, for our sakes (as at this time) manifested in the <hi>flesh;</hi> and not only so, but as the Apostle tells us, in <hi>the likeness of sinful flesh;</hi> tho without <hi>sin,</hi> yet<note place="margin">Rom. 8. 3.</note> like a sinner, so like, that to outward appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, no eye could discern any difference, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause subject to those <hi>miseries</hi> and <hi>necessities</hi> which are the consequences of sin in other men.</p>
            <p>WAS this a <hi>Manifestation?</hi> it was rather an <hi>Obscuration</hi> and vailing of his glory; yet mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fested he was, as the <hi>end,</hi> and <hi>design</hi> of the Work he was about requir'd; manifested to ignomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and reproach for sin: and this was one, and a great point of Christs humiliation, that <hi>he took not upon him the nature of Angels, but the seed</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 2. 6.</note>
               <hi>of Abraham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BUT we need not boggle at this, since it did
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152267:8"/> contribute to make him a more compleat <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our.</hi> In <hi>that it behoved Him to be made like unto his</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verse 17.</note>
               <hi>brethren, that he might he a merciful High Priest; And in that he suffered by being tempted, he is able to</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verse 18.</note>
               <hi>succour them also that are tempted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>RATHER, Let it prevail with us, to Praise <hi>God,</hi> for the great honour <hi>He</hi> hath confer'd upon our <hi>Nature</hi> in the <hi>Flesh</hi> of <hi>his Son,</hi> which in <hi>him,</hi> is <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed</hi> with more <hi>grace</hi> and <hi>glory,</hi> and fill'd with more Vast and Unmatchable Perfections, than all the <hi>Angels</hi> in <hi>Heaven,</hi> are together capable of, <hi>for,</hi> tho' for a while, <hi>He</hi> was made <hi>lower than the</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verse 9.</note>
               <hi>Angels,</hi> for the Purpose of <hi>his suffering; yet, he is</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 22.</note>
               <hi>now set down on the right hand, of the Majesty on high; Angels, Principalities,</hi> and <hi>Powers, being</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephes. 1. 21.</note>
               <hi>made Subject unto Him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THIS Indeed, should make us put a greater Value upon this <hi>flesh</hi> of ours, than to prostitute <hi>it,</hi> to mean and dishonourable services. It should make <hi>us</hi> labour to preserve it <hi>pure,</hi> and <hi>unspotted,</hi> and to <hi>glorifie God in our bodies,</hi> as well <hi>as in our</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 6. 20.</note>
               <hi>spirits, which are his.</hi> It should perswade <hi>us,</hi> to live no longer to our selves, as <hi>Men,</hi> after our<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3. 3.</note> own <hi>lusts,</hi> and <hi>ways,</hi> but <hi>as Men</hi> that are <hi>not their own,</hi> but <hi>his that bought them;</hi> to live in his service, and to his glory.</p>
            <p>THIS will be <hi>likewise</hi> the best course we can take to hearten <hi>us,</hi> against this <hi>Voice,</hi> in the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152267:8"/> Text, but neither this, nor ought else, can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt <hi>us</hi> from the comon lot of <hi>all flesh,</hi> which the Text assures us, is <hi>but grass, and all the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liness thereof as the flower of the field; the grass wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thereth, the flower fadeth,</hi> which in other <hi>words</hi> is no more, nor less than this, <hi>it is appointed for</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 27.</note>
               <hi>all Men once to die.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ALL <hi>Flesh is grass,</hi> All that we see, all that we admire, all the most Tempting Objects, we gaze and dote upon, yea the whole World, and all that is therein, is all but <hi>flesh,</hi> and all <hi>flesh is grass.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BUT, Is this a Truth <hi>so</hi> Universal, that it ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of no exception? tho' it may hold good, as to the generality of Men, yet are not the <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Monarchs,</hi> and <hi>Heroes</hi> of the <hi>World</hi> exempted? have not they <hi>something</hi> in them, that may Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge them, against the Insults, at least, of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Terrors? something,</hi> that they may (upon occasion) plead against the <hi>common Fate? The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> seems to agree to all this, and in the very Text, makes some difference between a <hi>mean</hi> and a <hi>great Person,</hi> between a <hi>Subject</hi> and a <hi>Prince;</hi> but what is it? No other, than is between green <hi>grass</hi> and a <hi>flower; Which,</hi> tho' more <hi>beautiful</hi> to the Eye, more <hi>sweet</hi> and <hi>pleasing</hi> to the Sense, is yet, every whit as <hi>fadeing,</hi> as <hi>perishing;</hi> and as <hi>sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> to be trod under foot, or to be scorch'd and wither'd by the <hi>Sun,</hi> as the <hi>grass</hi> is: <hi>As</hi> they grow
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152267:9"/> together in the same <hi>field,</hi> so they are equally liable to be cut down by the edge of the same <hi>Syth:</hi> and therefore it is, that the <hi>Prophet</hi> after the <hi>Voice</hi> had cried, <hi>All flesh is grass,</hi> adds, <hi>and all the goodliness of it, is as the flower of the field.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY the <hi>goodliness</hi> of the <hi>flesh,</hi> he means it's <hi>Youth,</hi> it's <hi>Health,</hi> it's <hi>Vigour,</hi> or whatever else in <hi>it,</hi> is most Valuable, and Pleasing. By <hi>it,</hi> we may understand the <hi>state,</hi> and <hi>condition</hi> of a Man that wants <hi>nothing, Nay,</hi> that abounds in all <hi>things</hi> the World can afford: As <hi>Riches, Honour,</hi> and <hi>Pleasure. Flesh,</hi> saith the <hi>Prophet, in all the glory of it,</hi> in the free and full injoyment of all things on the highest <hi>pinnacle</hi> of honour, seated upon a <hi>Throne,</hi> crowned with Diadems, and incircled, with all the Badges of Royalty and Grandeur; yet, in the midst of all this <hi>Pomp</hi> and <hi>Splendor,</hi> it's still but <hi>flesh,</hi> and liable to such damping thoughts as these.</p>
            <p>MAY not God this very night, take me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, like the <hi>Fool</hi> in the Gospel, from all these things, or these from me? May I not, nay, must I not, within these few years, it may be, within these few weeks, or days, instead of my <hi>honour,</hi> be laid in the dust? instead of my <hi>Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> and <hi>Scarlet,</hi> be cloathed with <hi>rottenness?</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of my <hi>Luxuries</hi> and <hi>Delicacies,</hi> become my self the food of Worms? Is not the poor <hi>Soul</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:152267:9"/> in my bosome, an <hi>Immortal soul?</hi> must it not have a <hi>being</hi> so long as there's a <hi>God,</hi> who is able to sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port <hi>it?</hi> And will not the <hi>gayeties</hi> of my <hi>flesh,</hi> and the <hi>ornaments</hi> of my <hi>mind,</hi> my <hi>baggs,</hi> and my <hi>titles,</hi> my <hi>pleasures,</hi> and my <hi>preferments,</hi> my ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>learning,</hi> and my <hi>natural endowments,</hi> and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>thing,</hi> save my <hi>sins (which</hi> I must then <hi>reckon for</hi>) forsake me, when I enter into that <hi>Immortality?</hi> I say when a Man shall take himself thus to <hi>task,</hi> and his heart <hi>summons</hi> him, to such <hi>serious thoughts</hi> as <hi>these;</hi> How will he be <hi>starttl'd</hi> and <hi>amaz'd,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>Sense,</hi> of his own <hi>Frailty,</hi> and his little <hi>hopes</hi> of a <hi>better State?</hi> And, how dreadful, will it be, for his <hi>Immortal Soul,</hi> to have nothing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>it,</hi> and <hi>Eternal Misery,</hi> but that, which will crumble and moulder, into <hi>dust,</hi> and leave the poor <hi>soul</hi> that trusted to <hi>it,</hi> to sink into bottom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less <hi>calamities.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor do our earthly <hi>injoyments</hi> always con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue with us, even to the <hi>last;</hi> but often leave <hi>us,</hi> before <hi>we</hi> our <hi>selves</hi> go <hi>off. Riches makes themselves Wings, Honour</hi> is fadeing, <hi>Wit, Beauty,</hi> and <hi>Strength</hi> fail, all Created Delights will quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have an <hi>End;</hi> and the Casualties that attend their very Enjoyment, doth sufficiently discover their <hi>Vanity,</hi> and the little <hi>stress,</hi> that's to be laid upon them: One <hi>Rich</hi> to day, and <hi>Poor</hi> to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row; in <hi>Health, Sound,</hi> and <hi>Strong,</hi> to day, to mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row <hi>Languishing</hi> and <hi>Expiring</hi> on a <hi>sick Bed;</hi> now
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152267:10"/> advanc'd to the high'st <hi>Pinnacle</hi> of <hi>Honour,</hi> anon deprest, and expos'd to <hi>Infamy,</hi> and <hi>Disgrace,;</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by Trains of <hi>Parasites</hi> and <hi>Flatterers,</hi> to day, to morrow <hi>deserted, slighted,</hi> and <hi>forsaken,</hi> by <hi>all:</hi> And as it is with <hi>Men,</hi> so it is with <hi>Things. Cities, Towns,</hi> and <hi>Villages, Flourishing</hi> and <hi>Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful, Rich</hi> and <hi>Opulent,</hi> to day, to morrow laid in <hi>Ashes,</hi> and <hi>levell'd</hi> with the <hi>ground.</hi> So that there's no <hi>Flower</hi> more fading, no <hi>Bubble,</hi> more vanishing, no <hi>Dream,</hi> more deluding, nothing more <hi>Vain,</hi> nothing more <hi>uncertain</hi> than the <hi>World</hi> is. <hi>It's all but grass,</hi> or at best <hi>but as the flower of the field; the grass withereth, the flower fadeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in the mid'st of all this <hi>Misery, Vanity,</hi> and <hi>Ʋncertainty.</hi> The <hi>Prophet</hi> adds, what may <hi>stay,</hi> and <hi>support</hi> us, <hi>But the word of our God shall stand for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ALL that's in the <hi>World, all</hi> the happiness that, <hi>that Flesh,</hi> which is but <hi>grass,</hi> can pretend to in its passage <hi>here,</hi> is full of <hi>Vanity, Ʋncertainty,</hi> and <hi>Disapointments,</hi> and then usually fail a <hi>Man</hi> most, when he most of all relies on them; which must needs be one of the greatest <hi>Defeats</hi> that can be. <hi>For,</hi> those things wherein Men fear <hi>Miscarriage,</hi> or expect <hi>Disapointment,</hi> they prepare such a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sposition of <hi>mind,</hi> as may be fit to bear it; but when a <hi>Man</hi> is surpriz'd with <hi>evil,</hi> when that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens which he least expected, the <hi>Novelty</hi> increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth the trouble: And the <hi>Scripture</hi> expresseth the greatness
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152267:10"/> ness of a Judgment, by the unexpectedness of it; <hi>When thou didst terrible things which we look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 6. 4▪ 3.</note>
               <hi>not for.</hi> Their not looking for it, rendred the Judgment so much the more terrible. <hi>A Breach in an instant, a momentary, a sudden destruction, a swift Damnation, a flying Role, a winged Woman,</hi> are all Expressions to denote a severe Judgment. Now Men are too too apt to promise themselves much Content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Satisfaction in the fruition of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly things; and to be herein disappointed (as they usually are) must needs be a great sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize, and occasion no small vexation.</p>
            <p>BUT the Word of God is <hi>an abiding Word,</hi> as founded on the Immutability of Gods own Truth, he that makes it his Refuge, relies on the Omnipotency of God himself; and has all the Strength of the Almighty, ingag'd to help him. <hi>Asa</hi> was safe while he depended up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God in his Promises, against the huge <hi>Hosts of the Ethiopians and Lubims;</hi> but when<note place="margin">2 Chron. 16. 7, 8, 9.</note> he turned aside to other aids, and trusted too much in the Arm of Flesh, he purchased to himself nothing but perpetual Wars. And this was that which established the Throne of <hi>Jehoshaphat,</hi> and caused <hi>the fear of the Lord to</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 17. 9. 11.</note>
               <hi>fall on all the Kingdoms of the Land, that were round about him;</hi> because he honour'd the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152267:11"/> Word of God, and caused it to be taught to his People. When <hi>Israel and Judah,</hi> did at any time forget to lean upon Gods Word, and betook themselves to correspondence with Idolatrous People, or other the like helps, they found themselves always bereft of succour; and all their hopes deceived and blasted. Which should teach us not to rest upon our own Wisdom, nor lean upon our own Strength, nor build our hopes and assurances upon Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Foundations; but in all Conditions, lay Hold upon <hi>Gods Word,</hi> which shall stand for Ever, and support us in any Extremity, and carry us, <hi>Through the valley of the shadow</hi>
               <note place="margin">Psal. 23. 4.</note>
               <hi>of death it self.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND thus I have done with what I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign'd to offer from the Text, but to apply it to the Occasion, I know neither how to begin nor where to end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Voice said, Cry.</hi> BUT how many Voices now Cry? The Church Cries, O my <hi>Protectress!</hi> The State Cries, O my <hi>Supportress!</hi> The King Cries, O the Friend of my Bosome, the Joy of my Life, the Companion of my Youth, the Sharer in my Joys, the Comfort in my Troubles, the Directress in my Counsels! The Court Cries, my <hi>Darling,</hi> my <hi>Delight,</hi> my <hi>Crown,</hi> and my <hi>Glory!</hi> The Subject Cries, my <hi>Shield,</hi> my
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152267:11"/>
               <hi>Defence,</hi> the joynt <hi>Author</hi> of my present Peace, the <hi>Foundress</hi> of my Happiness, the <hi>Defender,</hi> the <hi>Promoter,</hi> and (in some sense) the <hi>Resto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer</hi> of my Religion; The most Careful▪ Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, the most Tender and Indulgent Queen, and in all respects my <hi>Parent!</hi> But all these distinct Voices that compose the several Notes of this Mournful Harmony, do all meet, and joyn, and end in this Chorus, <hi>All flesh is grass, and all the glory therof as the flower of the Field.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE <hi>Voice</hi> Cries so <hi>Loud,</hi> and the Blow (tho' for our Sins justly inflicted) is every way so amazing, that the very thoughts of it were enough to make a Man lose all me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, tho' he had studied it never so care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully.</p>
            <p>AND therefore, That I may neither confound you, nor lose my self, I shall on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly glance at some few things, that may satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie us, what great Advantages we might have reapt from her <hi>Life,</hi> had it pleas'd the Wise Disposer of all things to have continued it. And this will naturally tend:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First.</hi> To give us a due sense of our loss.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:152267:12"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> To quicken us to such Duties, whereby (since 'tis impossible to improve it to our Temporal Advantage) we may yet make the best of it, that our Misfortune as well as our other Circumstances will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit.</p>
            <p>ALL that know me, can tell, I neither love nor use to offer any thing from this place by <hi>Hearsay,</hi> and yet it cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, that I had the Honour of any such <hi>Access,</hi> as to capacitate me to say much, from my own immediate knowledg. But yet this need not discourage me now; since I could easily say more, than what the time would allow, and nothing but what we all know to be true.</p>
            <p>I AM not insensible, how the glozeing Tongues of some <hi>Mercenary Orators,</hi> have Preached both themselves, and these kind of Discourses quite out of credit; as if their design were only to garnish a Dish for Worms, to make a trimming for the Grave, and paint for the Chambers of Death; but all Wise Men know the Vanity of such Varnish, and Colours thus laid on, give no Complexion to a judicious Eye; And how miserably will
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:152267:12"/> such Paint melt and drop away, and leave some faces horribly appal'd in that great day of the Lord? When the mouth of all wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edness shall be stopped, when Funeral Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons shall be shut, and those other <hi>Books</hi> (Books that cannot err) shall be opened, and the Dead judged by them.</p>
            <p>AND therefore there's nothing Ministers should more avoid, than courting and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plimenting with the Dead and Living too in Funeral Sermons, making them rather Harangues of Commendation to the Dead, than any serious Summons and Alarums to the Living; when it may be, neither the Life, nor the Death of the Deceased, gave any Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of such grace or comfort, as deserves either the imitation or the commendation of the Living.</p>
            <p>BUT I'm resolv'd to be innocent from this great <hi>Offence,</hi> which is the <hi>Reproach,</hi> and may prove the <hi>Ruin</hi> of these kind of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons. At least I need not fear it now, since if I had so little <hi>Integrity,</hi> that I would, yet that incomparable <hi>Queen,</hi> whose loss we now deplore, had so much <hi>Excellency,</hi> that I could not flatter.</p>
            <p>THE loss of a good (tho' private) Person, is at all times, especially, in bad times, a just
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152267:13"/> ground of deep sorrow; What then must be the loss of a good Queen, who is a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Stock, in which millions have a share? A burning <hi>Lamp,</hi> which shin'd and impart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed its Light to Three Great Kingdoms? No wonder if the exhausting of such a Store, the quenching of such a Lamp, should be matter of doleful complaint.</p>
            <p>AND here I could willingly indulge both yours and my own passion, that we might sit down a while in silence, and only by the Language of our Tears speak our sense of this heavy, this irreparable loss: But all Passions, especially that of <hi>Grief,</hi> need rather a Bridle than a Spurr; and we have some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elfe to do upon such an extraordinary occasion, than to bewaile our loss after the common rate, tho' that's allowed us too.</p>
            <p>A BRIGHT Star is removed; nay, our Sun is set: well may Darkness over-spread our Horrizon; <hi>A Cedar is fallen,</hi> well may<note place="margin">Zech. 11. 2.</note> the <hi>Fir-trees howl.</hi> A <hi>Cedar,</hi> which had God so pleased, might have stood and flourished much longer: But we often see the loftiest Cedar cut down before the useless Shrub, and they frequently fall (says one) who while they stood, not only graced the Forrest,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152267:13"/> but gave shade and shelter to others too. And oh! that we had not now the Occasion to bewail the Fall of the most Flourishing <hi>Plant,</hi> that grac'd our own or any other Soil; verify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that of St. <hi>Paul, The fashion of this world</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 7. 31.</note>
               <hi>passeth away;</hi> and we together with it. The Throne leaves some, and others leaves it; and as there is <hi>but one Kingdom which cannot be sha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12. 28.</note> Eternal in the Heavens; so there is but one King, the Immortal King of Ages, <hi>God</hi> over all, blessed for ever. All the rest are but <hi>flesh,</hi> and <hi>All flesh is grass.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AFTER such a Voice, what can warrant any of you that you shall be alive while too morrow? Who can be security for his own life one moment beyond the present? You'll say my Youth, my Strength, my Temperance, and my Vigour, these will secure me: But was there ever any, more healthy, more lively, more temperate, or more vigorous than the Queen? How sprightly, how fair, how hail, how charm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, was she but this day three Weeks, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most a Week after? And yet the King of Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors stole upon her, before her self, or at least, her friends suspected, being even (after some days illness) look'd upon as safe, and past all danger, on Tuesday; and yet, beyond all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation given over, and the Sentence of Death
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152267:14"/> pronounc'd by her Physicians, before Noon on Wednesday. <hi>So vain a thing is Man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BUT yet this can be no surprize to those, whose usual exercise it is to die daily; and as St. <hi>Ambrose</hi> conceived of <hi>Valentinian</hi> the Emperour, so may we of her Majesty; The Evidences past in her health, are fair Proofs of that Disposition her Soul was in, in her Sickness. But more of this anon; for tho all her earthly advantages are now become the spoils of Mortality, yet she's not to be laid in the Dust like Common Mold, nor deposited in the Shades with silence.</p>
            <p>IT's true; in the Blessed State to which she is now arrived, crowned with an Incorruptible Diadem, in the Company of Angels and Saints, and all her Triumphant Ancestors; she needs no praises of ours; but yet, that, which every good man may claim, is much more justly her due; Commendation after Death, being a Just Tribute to a Religious Life.</p>
            <p>CONSULT the Scriptures, and you shall scarce find one Godly Man laid in his Grave without an Epitaph of Honour; view the Fathers, and you shall observe it their practice, to honour the Death of the Good, especially of Princes; and if this had never been done before, it might be now allow'd to her, who was as well the best, as the greatest among Women. 'Twere
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152267:14"/> easie to shew it, in the Instances of her Illustrious Birth (being descended from a Royal Race of Kings, as well the greatest, as of the longest and most interrupted Succession now in the Christian World) in her Suitable Edueation, in her Natural and Acquired Accomplishments; which rendred her the Darling of the Age, as well as the Glory of her Sex. But we must leave these, and many other Advantages, with all her great Actions, to fill up Chronicles; and they will better become the History and Annals of the Age, than the Nook of a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</p>
            <p>THE Sweetness of her Temper, her Beauty, Wit, and Charms of Conversation, which made her like <hi>Vespasian, Deliciae humani generis,</hi> and rendred her Amiable and Dear, to all that had the honour to know her (tho they were Gifts from above) yet must they now be past over in silence, as being <hi>Praeda Mortis;</hi> A Spoil unto Death and the Grave.</p>
            <p>WHICH Consideration, should cure the undue Esteem, which too many Christians seem to put upon them; being more ambitious to outvy others in every thing, rather than real Holiness; which (after all's done) is the only Ornament that Death cannot spoil us of.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:152267:15"/>
            <p>NOR were the Endowments of her Mind any whit inferiour to those of her great Birth, and other Personal Advantages; Her Appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hension more quick and lively; her Judgment more penetrating and solid, her Elocution more ready, fluent, graceful, and every way more perswading, than is usually found in her Sex. And what good use <hi>She</hi> made of these Talents, I need not tell you; and it may justly upbraid many other Ladies, even of the First Rank, who (I know not upon what pretences) omit improving them the same way.</p>
            <p>I AM sure she had more <hi>Business</hi> to divert her, more <hi>Plenty</hi> and <hi>Abundance</hi> to entertain her, as much <hi>Beauty</hi> to tempt her, and more <hi>Favour</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> to intangle her, than any of them all; and liv'd in the same Atheistical degenerate Age that they live in. An Age wherein a sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere and serious, a religious and devout Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, is expos'd to <hi>Ridicule,</hi> and esteem'd the most unmodish, unfashionable, and useless thing that can be.</p>
            <p>AND yet all these disadvantages, all these temptations to raise her Pride, and make her haughty, to render her careless, secure, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devout; serv'd only to raise her Ambition, to behave her self more agreeable to her great Quality, by a Carriage truly exemplary, and
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:152267:15"/> every way great; A Carriage, that was in all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects, religious, honourable, and vertuous.</p>
            <p>HER Circumstances, we know, were such as would have allowed her to have indulg'd her self in a great many of the Vanities, which a loose and sinful Age might prompt her to. But these she always look'd upon with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est indifference and contempt imaginable. She was no enemy to the Modes and innocent Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoms of her Countrey, but yet us'd them with so much indifference and unconcernedness, as to her self, that could not but discover the lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle value she put upon them; Her Dress always modest and becoming, and suited more to her Quality than the <hi>Mode;</hi> that is, more rich than gay, and without the addition of Artificial Handsomness; which, as she needed it not, so neither would she censure, or restrain the liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of those that did: But she had that within, the Ornament of a meek but great Spirit; which was more truly valuable, and wherein she did every way excel.</p>
            <p>THE Great God of Heaven, the Creator and Disposer of all things, was chiefly regard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in all her Behaviour; and the first and main Principle of all her Actions.</p>
            <p>HENCE sprung that awful regard and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence of his Divine Majesty, which was vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152267:16"/> in all her Carriage; and I have heard, that <hi>She</hi> us'd frequently to express a great sense of the Folly, the Ignorance, and Impudence, of those (tho esteem'd Wits) who pretend to deny the being of a Deity; when they had such clear Convictions of Him, his Attributes, and Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, in every particular of the Creation; even such as were obvious and discoverable to their very Senses. And as no Pulpit Discourses pleas'd her better, than such as were dexterously levell'd against this unreasonable, this hellish Error; so for prevention of its growth, in an age so fruitful in evil, they were always com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to the Press.</p>
            <p>IT was upon this Belief, upon this Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge (as the best Foundation) that she rear'd that Noble Structure of Piety and Devotion, Uprightness and Sincerity, Purity and Charity, and all other the Duties of Christianity, that shined so brightly thro the whole Course of her Life.</p>
            <p>BUT by a Discourse, Just come to my<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Wake</hi>'s Sermon, at <hi>Grays.</hi> Inn, on the same occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.</note> hands, I find my self prevented, and every way out-done, as to what I offer'd upon these Heads; therefore, I chose rather to refer the Reader to it; and the rather because that Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend <hi>Author</hi> speaks <hi>all</hi> or <hi>most</hi> from his own knowledge, which may render it more Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152267:16"/> and more Satisfactory to him: and (as <hi>He himself</hi> observes) the Reader need not fear <hi>his</hi> imposing on him; for he may Defie <hi>him</hi> to flatter, if he would.</p>
            <p>THERE, you may behold this Great <hi>Queen</hi> Delineated at large. You may see how <hi>Great,</hi> how <hi>Good,</hi> how every way <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary</hi> She was in Her <hi>Life,</hi> and no less so, in Her <hi>Death;</hi> being an Object not lightly to be laid to all our Hearts, not only as <hi>Subjects,</hi> not only as <hi>Christians,</hi> but as <hi>Men,</hi> as <hi>Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals</hi> too; warning all that have <hi>seen</hi> or shall <hi>hear</hi> of the sudden blasting of this <hi>Flower, that all flesh is grass,</hi> and louder than any other <hi>Voice</hi> crys, <hi>All the goodliness thereof</hi> is but as <hi>the flower of the field.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THERE, you may see how great a Friend She was to the <hi>Church,</hi> how careful of the welfare of the <hi>State,</hi> and how much She did contribute to the <hi>Hapiness</hi> of <hi>both.</hi> How Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious, how Pious, in <hi>Publick:</hi> how Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>act, How Punctual in <hi>Private:</hi> How constant in the <hi>Chappel:</hi> How frequent in the <hi>Closet:</hi> and how <hi>Sincere</hi> and <hi>Devout</hi> in both.</p>
            <p>I HAD once the Honour to be near Her, when She received the Blessed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and I shall never forget, with what <hi>Reverence,</hi> what <hi>Humility,</hi> what <hi>Zeal</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention,</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:152267:17"/> She did Participate of that Divine <hi>Mistery;</hi> which plainly shewed, She was as <hi>Sincerely</hi> as <hi>Seemingly,</hi> Devout.</p>
            <p>HER <hi>Affections</hi> seem'd to be raised above their common pitch, and Her <hi>Carriage,</hi> du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the whole <hi>Action,</hi> was so Heavenly and so Divine; as if Her <hi>Soul</hi> had actually ascended to that <hi>God,</hi> to whom Her <hi>Prayers</hi> were di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected: And brought to my thoughts, that saying of St. <hi>Lukes,</hi> concerning St. <hi>Stephen,</hi> when he saw the Heavens opened, and <hi>Jesus</hi> standing at Gods Right Hand. <hi>His face,</hi> says the Text, <hi>was as the face of an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND now, <hi>She,</hi> that by such remarkable Instances of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Devotion,</hi> Manifested the Profound Reverence and Veneration <hi>She</hi> had for God, could not be wanting in any regard to the rest of his Commandments: <hi>She</hi> that was so exact in the Duties of the <hi>First,</hi> could not be defective in those of the <hi>Second</hi> Table. Her <hi>Righteousness</hi> was no <hi>Less</hi> Illustrious in that respect, than Her <hi>Piety</hi> was in the other.</p>
            <p>HER <hi>Word</hi> was as Sacred as any <hi>Oath,</hi> and no inconvenience would make Her flinch from what <hi>She</hi> had once promised. <hi>She</hi> so much abhorred a Dishonorable <hi>Recess,</hi> that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:152267:17"/>
               <hi>She</hi> had no great <hi>Value</hi> for those, who by <hi>Little</hi> Arts and Shifts would free themselves from their Ingagements; and thereby disap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point the <hi>Expectations</hi> they had raised in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>BUT I need not stay upon this. Her Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues in this kind were <hi>so</hi> Eminent, and <hi>so</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spicuous, that (considering the <hi>Orb</hi> She shone in) it was impossible they could be conceal'd: And this was it, that made Her so justly Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired, and so entirely Beloved of all.</p>
            <p>She was of that Sweetness of Temper, of that Kindness, Affability, and (considering Her great Quality) of that Condiscension and Courtesie, in all Her <hi>Demeanour,</hi> as rendered Her very <hi>Dear,</hi> and Her <hi>Conversation</hi> very Grateful, and Desirable, to all that had the <hi>Honour</hi> to be near Her.</p>
            <p>SHE was usually very Pleasant and Chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, but Her Mirth was always managed with Discretion, and bounded with Religion; Her Prudence kept her within the limits of <hi>Reason,</hi> and her <hi>Piety</hi> restrained her from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Vain:</hi> In both <hi>which,</hi> She was very <hi>Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent,</hi> and very <hi>Exemplary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SHE was in <hi>Her</hi> Conversation (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the <hi>Respect</hi> due to her Quality) far from ingrossing all the Discourse to her self:
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152267:18"/> And when <hi>She</hi> did speak <hi>She</hi> still (according to the Wise Mans Character of the good <hi>Woman) opened her mouth with wisdom, and in</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 31. 26.</note>
               <hi>her tongue was the Law of kindness.</hi> And She did so far excel all others <hi>this</hi> way, that, if a <hi>Stranger,</hi> who had never seen her, had come in, and found her at work among her Maids of <hi>Honour</hi> (as he often might) or in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of other Ladies, without any Badges of Royalty and Distinction: He had been very <hi>Ʋndiscerning,</hi> if (after a little observation ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of her graceful <hi>Meen;</hi> or winning way of <hi>Address</hi>) he had not presently concluded, <hi>That's the</hi> QUEEN. In a <hi>Word,</hi> She was so great a <hi>Proficient</hi> in all the Arts of Obliging, that She Reigned over the <hi>Hearts,</hi> as well as the <hi>Persons,</hi> of all those, who were happy in the Honour of her Converse.</p>
            <p>AND now, <hi>She</hi> who was thus <hi>Exact,</hi> thus <hi>Perfect,</hi> in all the Duties both of the <hi>First</hi> and <hi>Second</hi> Table, must needs <hi>Excel</hi> in <hi>that</hi> which is the great <hi>Badge</hi> and <hi>Character</hi> of them all, <hi>Charity;</hi> of which She was so <hi>Compleat</hi> a <hi>Pattern,</hi> that, if She out-did her <hi>Self</hi> in any one <hi>Thing,</hi> it was in this; which She extended both to the Persons and Necessities of <hi>all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being all <hi>Goodness</hi> her self, She was apt to believe most People <hi>Good</hi> too, or at least, bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152267:18"/> than perhaps they were; <hi>Charity thinking</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13. 6.</note>
               <hi>no evil.</hi> And <hi>She</hi> used this good opinion of others, as an <hi>Instrument</hi> to make them, what <hi>She</hi> was so willing to signifie She thought them. She would never diminish the just prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses of any that deserved them; nay, would rather lessen their other failings, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend them for some one good quality, to cover a great many bad ones: And so would make People good by believing them to be so, and by this ingagement make them asha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to deceive or disappoint her expectation, and thoughts of them.</p>
            <p>AND then, as to the <hi>Necessities</hi> of others, She was <hi>willing to Her Power, yea and beyond</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8. 3.</note>
               <hi>her Power,</hi> to relieve them. God who always <hi>Honours them, that honour him,</hi> had given<note place="margin">1 Sam. 2. 30.</note> her <hi>Riches and Honour in abundance,</hi> as is said of King <hi>Jehoshaphat.</hi> Yet her <hi>Heart</hi> was not<note place="margin">2 Chron. 17. 5. Vers. 6.</note> puffed up by them, <hi>but lifted up under them in the ways of the Lord.</hi> And the great satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction She took in them, was the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity they afforded her of doing <hi>Good;</hi> and when at any time they would not answer the great <hi>Designs</hi> of her <hi>Willing Soul,</hi> the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned discourse tells us, what her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern<note place="margin">Pag. 36.</note> and regret was.</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:152267:19"/>
            <p>SHE had a deep Sense of the <hi>Wants</hi> of all Persons, and would catch at the least hint of any proper <hi>Object</hi> of <hi>Charity,</hi> when at any time mentioned; and never declin'd relieving any <hi>Indigent,</hi> either <hi>Families</hi> or private <hi>Persons,</hi> when recommended to her.</p>
            <p>NOR was her Charity confined only to such <hi>Here,</hi> but extended to <hi>Ireland</hi> too; and not only to those <hi>there,</hi> who had suffered for being Protestants, or for espousing her Interest; but even to the <hi>Irish Orphans,</hi> that is, the <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> of such <hi>Parents</hi> who died in actual Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, and Fighting against <hi>Her;</hi> and <hi>That,</hi> after they had Robb'd, and Stripp'd, and Kill'd, and Murdered many of Her Loyal Subjects: Yet to their <hi>Children,</hi> was her great <hi>Charity</hi> design'd: And She was (to my knowledge) very soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citous, to have some <hi>Fund</hi> settled for their sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, that they might be brought up in the Protestant Religion, and maintained, while fit to be put to Trades, or otherwise disposed of.</p>
            <p>THIS was <hi>Charity</hi> indeed, the doing <hi>Good</hi> for <hi>Gods sake,</hi> without any other than a <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian</hi> and truly <hi>Pious</hi> inducement, <hi>to lay up in</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6. 19.</note>
               <hi>store a good foundation against the time to come, And to make to her self friends of the Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luk. 16. 9.</note>
               <hi>of unrighteousness.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:152267:19"/>
            <p>SHE had a great compassion for such Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners as fled for their Religion, as being forward to <hi>do good to all,</hi> so especially to <hi>those of the Houshold of Faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BUT She had a particular concern for such indigent Persons, whose Circumstances had been any ways considerable in the World; there being some <hi>Objects</hi> of real <hi>Charity,</hi> which are not so to vulgar <hi>Eyes</hi> or <hi>Purses,</hi> on whom She would <hi>Confer,</hi> and whom She would <hi>Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize</hi> with great and suitable assistances; and to such, She was generally <hi>Kind</hi> in the very manner, as well as measure of her <hi>Charity;</hi> being as tender of their <hi>Modesty,</hi> as <hi>She</hi> was compassionate of their <hi>Necessity,</hi> and by her sweet obliging <hi>Way,</hi> made her <hi>Gift</hi> seem more a <hi>Present</hi> than a <hi>Charity.</hi> But I should never have done, should I <hi>insist</hi> on particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, or say all that might be said of <hi>Her</hi> in a <hi>Private</hi> Capacity, as a <hi>Christian.</hi> And how much more might be said of <hi>Her</hi> in <hi>Relation</hi> to others?</p>
            <p>AS She was the best of <hi>Queens,</hi> so She was the best of <hi>Mistresses,</hi> to those who had the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour</hi> to serve her; never (as I am informed) urging her commands upon them, so much by her <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Authority,</hi> as by obliging them by her <hi>Kindness</hi> and <hi>Condiscension;</hi> treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:152267:20"/> them more like <hi>Friends</hi> than <hi>Servants.</hi> And as their <hi>Quality</hi> did intitle many of <hi>them</hi> (as much as <hi>any</hi> of their fellow <hi>Subjects</hi>) to her <hi>Friendship,</hi> so She lost nothing by afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>it;</hi> but did secure their most ready <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> upon stronger <hi>Principles</hi> than that of bare <hi>Authority,</hi> even those of <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude;</hi> which as <hi>they</hi> are most acceptable and pleasant on all <hi>sides,</hi> so are <hi>they</hi> most <hi>Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> and most <hi>Lasting.</hi> In a word, I have been <hi>told</hi> that <hi>Her</hi> carriage among <hi>them</hi> was so <hi>Obliging</hi> and so <hi>Prudent,</hi> that <hi>She</hi> was never known to say or do any <hi>thing</hi> unworthy of her great <hi>Self,</hi> or unbecoming that great <hi>Wis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and <hi>Discretion</hi> that appeared in all her <hi>Actions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I SHALL now consider her as a <hi>Queen</hi> and that but briefly, fearing to out-strip my time. And first, As a <hi>Queen Consort,</hi> As a <hi>Wife:</hi> and here we may say as the Scripture says, <hi>The heart of her Husband did safely trust in her, and</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 31. 11, 12.</note>
               <hi>she did him good, and not evil, all the days of her life.</hi> Never was Woman more a <hi>Crown</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 12. 4.</note> and <hi>Ornament</hi> to Man. She lived, doubtless with a great <hi>Sense</hi> of the <hi>Covenant</hi> of God, that was betwixt <hi>Them,</hi> upon her <hi>Heart,</hi> and might say, as <hi>Her</hi> Royal <hi>Grandfather</hi> in his Message to his <hi>Queen,</hi> that she never trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grest
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152267:20"/> the <hi>Obligation</hi> of <hi>Fidelity</hi> or <hi>Affection</hi> to <hi>Him,</hi> no not in <hi>Thought.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>She</hi> was all <hi>Love,</hi> and all <hi>Obedience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A GREAT part of her care, was to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve every thing that was most pleasing to him, and she was in all respects what she ought to be, <hi>A help meet.</hi> And the inexpressible <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 2. 20.</note> His <hi>Majesty</hi> Groans under, for her <hi>Loss,</hi> is a too sufficient <hi>Manifestation</hi> of all this.</p>
            <p>AND upon this <hi>Head,</hi> it might not be improper to add a <hi>Word</hi> or two as a just and farther <hi>Vindication</hi> of Her <hi>Majesty</hi> in the only <hi>thing</hi> her most malicious Enemies could charge <hi>Her</hi> with.</p>
            <p>SHE, who was so generally and so justly <hi>beloved</hi> and <hi>admir'd</hi> by <hi>all,</hi> had yet the hard <hi>thoughts</hi> of some <hi>few</hi> Byast and Unreasonable <hi>Men;</hi> who pretended <hi>forsooth,</hi> to be dissatisfied with <hi>Her way</hi> of coming to the <hi>Crown;</hi> and were therefore so <hi>Impudent,</hi> as to <hi>Censure</hi> Her for <hi>it. But</hi> had there not been other great and weighty <hi>Reasons,</hi> yea an absolute <hi>necessity</hi> for it, as <hi>great</hi> as the <hi>saving</hi> Three tottering King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms from <hi>sinking,</hi> and our <hi>Religion, Laws,</hi> and <hi>Liberties,</hi> and after <hi>them,</hi> our <hi>Estates,</hi> and <hi>Lives</hi> from expiring. Had there been, <hi>I say,</hi> none of <hi>these</hi> or any other <hi>Inducements,</hi> yet the <hi>Obligations She</hi> lay under as a <hi>Wife</hi> (which by one
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152267:21"/> of the first <hi>Sanctions</hi> in Holy-Writ, are far<note place="margin">Gen. 2. 20.</note> greater, than any Due from a <hi>Child,</hi> to a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent</hi>) might very well have excused <hi>Her;</hi> and removed their <hi>dislike</hi> upon that <hi>score,</hi> and so rendred Her as <hi>amiable</hi> and <hi>dear,</hi> to them, as <hi>She</hi> was to all others.</p>
            <p>AND now we might consider Her as a <hi>Queen Regent.</hi> And <hi>here</hi> again, as a farther demonstration of His <hi>Majesties</hi> great <hi>Affection;</hi> when the aspiring <hi>Designs</hi> and <hi>Attempts,</hi> of a potent and haughty <hi>Enemy,</hi> forc'd Him from <hi>Her</hi> and <hi>us;</hi> and necessarily required <hi>His</hi> Presence elsewhere, He intrusted the whole Management of the <hi>State,</hi> to Her <hi>Care</hi> and <hi>Conduct;</hi> to which, tho' She was (in His ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sence) Qualified and Intituled by <hi>Law,</hi> yet, it was a high Testimony of his <hi>confidence</hi> in Her <hi>prudence,</hi> to leave and intrust it to Her sole <hi>Care.</hi> Which <hi>Trust</hi> She discharged with such <hi>Dexterity,</hi> such <hi>Exactness,</hi> and such ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable <hi>Wisdom;</hi> that She never gave or left <hi>occasion</hi> for any Complaint, but rendred <hi>all</hi> more than <hi>silent, satisfied;</hi> and not only <hi>satisfied,</hi> but <hi>applauding,</hi> and <hi>admiring</hi> her <hi>pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi> and <hi>honourable Conduct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND tho' She loved, and even hugg'd Her <hi>retirements</hi> as Her greatest <hi>satisfaction;</hi> yet when the <hi>Exigences</hi> of affairs requir'd <hi>it,</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:152267:21"/> She would deny her self, and her particular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination, to comply with a <hi>Duty</hi> of a more publick <hi>concern;</hi> and <hi>cheerfully</hi> sustained the hurry of <hi>Business,</hi> which was inevitable, and always acquitted her <hi>self</hi> (with <hi>honour</hi> and <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plause</hi>) of the great <hi>trust</hi> imposed in <hi>her.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But never did any man, after a long and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>easie confinement <hi>meet</hi> his <hi>liberty,</hi> with more <hi>joy</hi> and <hi>satisfaction,</hi> than she did solace her self, when she had escap'd the <hi>noise</hi> and <hi>croud</hi> of <hi>affairs</hi> which must needs have ruffled and disturb'd her <hi>quiet,</hi> and (so far) lessen'd (or at least) suspended the full <hi>injoyment</hi> of her <hi>self.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now by such a <hi>regular,</hi> such a <hi>pious,</hi> and such a <hi>righteous life,</hi> we cannot easily suspect <hi>she</hi> could be unprepar'd even for the most <hi>sudden</hi> death: and tho the warning was indeed but short; yet we have no reason to fear it was much <hi>surprizing</hi> to <hi>one</hi> that always lived in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation of <hi>it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She was always (as I was inform'd) in the midst of her <hi>health,</hi> and <hi>strength,</hi> apprehensive enough of the <hi>Disease</hi> whereof <hi>she</hi> died; yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing seiz'd with it, <hi>she</hi> seem'd not at all discou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rag'd, and profess'd her self intirely <hi>willing</hi> to acquiesce in the <hi>will</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> and all the while of her <hi>illness,</hi> continued in the same frame: and notwithstanding a complication of Distempers,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152267:22"/> notwithstanding the trouble someprescriptions of Physicians, and the no less troublesome applications of others; notwithstanding her own <hi>Pain</hi> and <hi>Disorder;</hi> of which (her Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution, and other Circumstances consider'd) <hi>She</hi> could not but be <hi>very</hi> sensible, yet with an admirable <hi>Patience</hi> and <hi>Resignation</hi> to the <hi>Will</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> with a great contempt of the <hi>Vanities</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> and with a Holy indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference even, to <hi>Life</hi> it self; <hi>She</hi> was ready to answer, when it pleased God to call: being impatient in <hi>nothing,</hi> nor importunate in any <hi>thing</hi> save an earnest <hi>desire</hi> that she might know her <hi>Danger;</hi> and when it was at last declared to her; O God! How like an <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel,</hi> rather than a <hi>Soul</hi> clogg'd with <hi>Flesh,</hi> did She receive <hi>it?</hi> With such an <hi>Humble</hi> uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernedness, such <hi>Submission,</hi> and such even<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness of <hi>Temper;</hi> as <hi>nothing</hi> could have given, <hi>but</hi> an Innocent and Meek <hi>Spirit,</hi> and a <hi>Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence void of offence, towards God and towards man.</hi> And resigned up Her great <hi>Soul</hi> in <hi>Death,</hi> with the same <hi>courage,</hi> and the same <hi>quietness,</hi> that She had possest <hi>it</hi> in <hi>patience</hi> all Her <hi>Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND thus <hi>Lived,</hi> and thus <hi>Died</hi> (who can speak it without <hi>tears?</hi>) this great <hi>Queen,</hi> this glorious <hi>Saint;</hi> tho' not full of <hi>Years,</hi> yet full of <hi>Mature Fruits</hi> and <hi>Graces:</hi> when all <hi>Men</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:152267:22"/> Judged Her worthy of a <hi>longer,</hi> but <hi>God,</hi> the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>unerring Judge,</hi> found Her full ripen'd for a better <hi>Life.</hi> And after He <hi>had prevented her with the blessings of goodness, and set a Crown of pure Gold upon her Head:</hi> After He had given Her the Universal <hi>Esteem, Love</hi> and <hi>Admiration,</hi> of all that knew <hi>Her;</hi> the <hi>blessing</hi> of a <hi>good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name;</hi> and more than unspotted; a <hi>bright</hi> and <hi>resplendent Reputation.</hi> After <hi>He had granted her the request of her lips, and shut not out her prayer.</hi> After <hi>He had made her glad with the light of his Countenance,</hi> and given Her the <hi>Heaven</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Earth,</hi> the blessing of a <hi>calm purified</hi> and <hi>well assured Conscience.</hi> In a <hi>word,</hi> After He had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out the <hi>Sting</hi> of <hi>Death,</hi> and made it an easie passage to <hi>Everlasting Life,</hi> He then took Her from her corruptible and <hi>Earthly,</hi> to an incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible and <hi>Heavenly Crown.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND She is now <hi>safely</hi> arriv'd in that <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Place,</hi> where (as the <hi>Father</hi> sweetly Warbles) there's <hi>Vita Aeterna, Beatitude Perfecta, &amp; Summa Voluptas;</hi> Fullness of Joy, Eternity of Life, and Perfection of Bliss. Where Her <hi>Faith</hi> is turned into <hi>Sight,</hi> Her <hi>Hope</hi> into <hi>Fruition,</hi> and <hi>Love,</hi> Everlastingly satisfied with the <hi>Presence</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Face</hi> of <hi>Jesus Christ,</hi> the <hi>Fulness</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> with the <hi>Communion</hi> and <hi>Society</hi> of all <hi>Saints,</hi> and the <hi>Spirits</hi> of Just <hi>Men</hi> made <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect;</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:152267:23"/> where all the <hi>Cares</hi> and <hi>Troubles</hi> annext to an Earthly <hi>Crown,</hi> are now done away; and where <hi>She is,</hi> and <hi>shall be</hi> for <hi>ever</hi> ravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed, in joyning with <hi>Angels</hi> and <hi>Saints,</hi> and all the <hi>Choir</hi> of <hi>Heaven,</hi> to Carrol forth <hi>Praises,</hi> and Sing <hi>Hallelujahs to him that sits upon the Throne, to the Lamb, and to God for ever. The</hi> most Glorious <hi>Imployment;</hi> the most Happy <hi>State▪</hi> that the greatest <hi>Monarch,</hi> the greatest <hi>Angel</hi> ever arrived to: And tho' it be every way Her <hi>Advantage</hi> and Her <hi>Gain,</hi> yet it's still our <hi>Loss,</hi> and Her many <hi>Excellencies</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, may satifie <hi>us,</hi> what great <hi>Advantages</hi> we might have expected from her Life, had it pleased the <hi>Almighty</hi> to have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued it.</p>
            <p>AND now let us suspend our <hi>Sorrow</hi> a while; and consider what may be <hi>justly</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from our <hi>Selves</hi> on this <hi>sad Occasion.</hi> And <hi>here</hi> I could lay before you a <hi>Pattern</hi> worthy of your imitation; such a <hi>Pattern,</hi> as, in all <hi>respects,</hi> this <hi>Age,</hi> perhaps, has not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced; A <hi>Patern</hi> that may for ever Silence, what, either the <hi>greatest</hi> or the <hi>meanest</hi> Person, can offer against the Reasonableness or the Necessity of a <hi>Holy Life:</hi> and may sufficiently convince <hi>us,</hi> that there are no insuperable difficulties in <hi>Religion;</hi> for tho' She was a <hi>Queen,</hi>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:152267:23"/> yet She was a <hi>Woman,</hi> of the feebler <hi>Sex;</hi> a Great and a Rich <hi>Woman, and how hardly can such</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 19. 23.</note>
               <hi>be saved?</hi> A <hi>Woman</hi> of like <hi>passions</hi> with your <hi>selves,</hi> inwardly clogged with the same cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and sinful <hi>Nature,</hi> outwardly beset with the like or greater <hi>Temptations;</hi> and yet She cast off the <hi>weight</hi> that hung upon <hi>Her,</hi> broke through the <hi>difficulties,</hi> that did incompass <hi>Her, and ran the Race, which was set before her;</hi> and <hi>through faith, and patience, hath obtained,</hi> and now <hi>Inherits the promises,</hi> and that <hi>sure re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> that <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>Glory,</hi> that <hi>endless Kingdom;</hi> which <hi>God</hi> hath provided, and <hi>Christ</hi> hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chased, and promised; to <hi>Her,</hi> and all <hi>Them</hi> that love and fear <hi>Him,</hi> and <hi>wait for his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I COULD <hi>likewise</hi> here show you, how idle and frothy are the <hi>Projects</hi> and <hi>Purposes,</hi> the <hi>Designs</hi> and <hi>Resolutions,</hi> which worldly <hi>Men</hi> are too too <hi>apt</hi> to propose to themselves on the <hi>Hopes,</hi> and to build upon the <hi>Assu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances</hi> of long <hi>Life;</hi> than which there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more <hi>Vain,</hi> nothing more <hi>Ʋncertain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IF ever any <hi>meer</hi> Mortal could by any pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge whatsoever, pretend or hope sor <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption</hi> from the Arrests of <hi>Death;</hi> This <hi>Good,</hi> this <hi>Great,</hi> this <hi>Young,</hi> this <hi>Healthy Queen</hi> might; and <hi>yet</hi> all the advantage <hi>She</hi> has now over
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152267:24"/> common <hi>Dust,</hi> is, that to <hi>Her</hi> may <hi>David</hi>'s La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation over <hi>Saul</hi> be more fitly applyed; <hi>O! how is the Mighty fallen? how lovely and pleasant</hi> was<note place="margin">2 Sam. 1. 19.</note> She in her <hi>Life?</hi> and yet She is <hi>fallen; as if She had not been Anointed with Oyle.</hi> And indeed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in the whole <hi>World,</hi> could have more convincingly assured <hi>us</hi> of this <hi>truth,</hi> that <hi>all flesh is grass,</hi> than Her <hi>Fall</hi> hath done.</p>
            <p>BUT I hasten to what yet remains▪</p>
            <p>THERE are two <hi>Duties</hi> that seem speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally and necessarily to be <hi>Incumbent</hi> upon us at this <hi>time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> WHAT we are to <hi>do</hi> to sanctifie, or at <hi>least</hi> how we are to demean our <hi>selves,</hi> that <hi>God</hi> may sanctifie this great <hi>Loss</hi> to <hi>us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> WHAT we are to <hi>Do</hi> to lessen it, so as it may not prove <hi>fatal</hi> to us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> HOW we are to Improve <hi>this</hi> so, as to have it sanctified to <hi>us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THIS is certain, by such dispensations as <hi>these,</hi> the <hi>Death</hi> of his <hi>Servants; God</hi> doth fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warn us of suture Judgments; especially, if they be such as are <hi>great</hi> and <hi>eminent,</hi> whether in <hi>Church</hi> or <hi>State:</hi> and we have <hi>now</hi> lost the <hi>Greatest</hi> in <hi>Both;</hi> And this is a fearful <hi>Sign</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:152267:24"/> that some heavy Judgment attends the Rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the <hi>People.</hi> This is that whereof our <hi>Prophet</hi> speaks, <hi>Behold the Lord, the Lord of Hosts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 3. 1, 2, 3.</note>
               <hi>doth take away from</hi> Jerusalem, <hi>the mighty man, and the man of War, the Judge, and the Prophet, and the Prudent, and the Ancient, the Captain of fifty, and the honourable man, and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seller;</hi> and all this threatned as the fore-runner of of heavy Judgments; such as the having <hi>children</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vers. 4, 5</note> for <hi>their Princes,</hi> their <hi>oppressing one another,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 8.</note> and no <hi>less</hi> than the <hi>ruin</hi> of <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> and <hi>the fall of Judah.</hi> And the same <hi>Prophet,</hi> elswhere tells us, <hi>That the Righteous perisheth, and no man layeth it to heart, and merciful men are taken away, none considering that they are taken</hi>
               <note place="margin">Isa. 57. 1.</note>
               <hi>from the evil to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THUS was that good King <hi>Josiah</hi> dealt with, not long after whose <hi>Death,</hi> followed the <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity</hi> of <hi>Babel.</hi> In the <hi>Grave</hi> wherein <hi>he</hi> was Interr'd, the <hi>Liberty, Glory,</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> of <hi>Jewry,</hi> lay also Buried.</p>
            <p>I Would not willingly be the <hi>Prophet</hi> of our <hi>Wo,</hi> but whatever we may <hi>think,</hi> or however we may <hi>flatter</hi> our selves, <hi>God</hi> never with-draws such <hi>great lights</hi> out of the World, but at the approach of some Black and Dreadful <hi>Tempest; which,</hi> if we <hi>humble</hi> not our <hi>selves,</hi> under his <hi>Mighty hand,</hi> and prepare to meet him in the
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152267:25"/>
               <hi>way of his Judgments</hi>) will certainly over-take us. And <hi>therefore</hi> while it is called <hi>to day,</hi> let us not <hi>harden our Hearts,</hi> but look to the <hi>Things</hi> that concerns our <hi>Peace.</hi> Let us <hi>Search and try our ways, and turn again unto the Lord.</hi> We cannot think he hath made this great <hi>Breach,</hi> only, to open a passage to our <hi>Sorrow,</hi> much <hi>less</hi> to furnish us with new matter of <hi>Discourse:</hi> No, <hi>He</hi> designs that we should glorifie him in our <hi>Hearts</hi> and <hi>Lives,</hi> more than formerly we have done; and therefore let it be our <hi>Wisdom</hi> and our <hi>Care,</hi> to <hi>Hear the rod, and who hath appointed it,</hi> to turn every Man from the <hi>Evil</hi> of his <hi>Way,</hi> before the Lords <hi>Wrath</hi> be farther kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and to <hi>repent</hi> and <hi>relent</hi> for <hi>all our trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gressions, that so Iniquity may not be our ruin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> LET us see how we may lessen this great <hi>Loss,</hi> at least, so <hi>far,</hi> as to prevent its being fatal to us. And I conceive, the best course we can take in order to <hi>this,</hi> is to put a double <hi>value</hi> upon <hi>Him,</hi> whom <hi>God</hi> in his mercy yet <hi>spares</hi> to us, <hi>Our Gracious King;</hi> let this Heavy Stroke, render His <hi>Life,</hi> more dear to us. Let us pray more constantly, and more fervently, for his <hi>health,</hi> his <hi>safety,</hi> his <hi>happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness,</hi> and his <hi>success.</hi> We may be induced <hi>strongly</hi> to <hi>this,</hi> upon these Grounds.</p>
            <pb n="49" facs="tcp:152267:25"/>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> WE we are to do <hi>this,</hi> for <hi>Her</hi> sake that is <hi>gone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> FOR His own <hi>sake.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> AND <hi>Especially</hi> upon the account of our selves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> FOR Her <hi>sake</hi> that's <hi>gone,</hi> While she lived, she <hi>Loved, Honoured</hi> and <hi>Admired</hi> him: She knew His <hi>Worth</hi> beyond what we do; and besides his many other <hi>Accomplishments,</hi> which his ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Enemies admire in <hi>Him;</hi> She knew, that in his greatest undertaking, <hi>He</hi> had no other <hi>Aim,</hi> or <hi>Interest,</hi> than the good of <hi>Europe,</hi> and espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially that part of it which needed most his help, and to which he was in all respects most obliged to give it; <hi>Great Britain</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN a <hi>Word,</hi> She best knew him, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore justly valued him: And surely if the Saints departed, have any knowledge of what passes here below, we cannot perform a more grateful <hi>Service</hi> to her <hi>Memory,</hi> than to value him, to <hi>Love, Honour</hi> and <hi>Admire</hi> him too.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> FOR his own sake. Remember he is a <hi>Prince</hi> that has got nothing by us, but <hi>Trouble,</hi> and <hi>Care,</hi> and <hi>Travel,</hi> and <hi>Toyl,</hi> and <hi>Danger;</hi> A <hi>Prince,</hi> who when we were in the extreamest danger, upon the <hi>Brink</hi> of being ruined and undone, staked his <hi>Life,</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:152267:26"/> his <hi>Fortune,</hi> his <hi>All,</hi> to save us; in which <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt</hi> (considering the <hi>Season,</hi> and the power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Army</hi> there was to oppose him, with the other <hi>Difficulties,</hi> he had to struggle with) the <hi>Discouragements</hi> were so many: that none but a <hi>Courage,</hi> great like his, could have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countred them: And indeed the undertaking was so great, and the means to carry it on, (in <hi>Proportion</hi> so little) that we need not think it an <hi>Hyperbole</hi> in him, who concludes, there was a Power more than Humane, in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to pass; and the <hi>Issue</hi> seems to confirm it. Insomuch that <hi>France</hi> her self, that laught at the <hi>Attempt,</hi> was yet amaz'd at the <hi>Success,</hi> and well she might; it being the likeliest step that was ever made towards her Ruine. But to return:</p>
            <p>REMEMBER, He is a <hi>Prince,</hi> who, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter many Years Effeminacy, Luxury, Ease, and Softness (wherein the <hi>English</hi> Valour so famed heretofore.) lay withering and fading, unactive and rusting) hath renewed to us, the Memory of those great <hi>Kings</hi> who Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>English Armies</hi> abroad, and hath done more in his own <hi>Person,</hi> than all the CROWNED Heads of this, or (for ought I know) any other <hi>Age.</hi> What <hi>Prince</hi> ever so oft exposed to the <hi>Dangers</hi> of the <hi>Sea,</hi> as well as to the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:152267:26"/>
               <hi>Plots</hi> of <hi>Assassines,</hi> and the <hi>Arms</hi> of the <hi>Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> by <hi>Land?</hi> As <hi>He</hi> has been.</p>
            <p>A PRINCE, That as always, so lately, and especially in the Reduction of <hi>Ireland,</hi> hath made good the <hi>Character</hi> of <hi>His</hi> Illustrious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, in being the <hi>Deliverer</hi> of oppressed <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> In a word, A <hi>Prince,</hi> who hath every way performed his part; how much soever his Affairs hath been clogged at <hi>Home,</hi> by the unnatural Treachery of <hi>some,</hi> who like the true <hi>Seed</hi> of <hi>Nero,</hi> can rake with delight in the Bowels of their <hi>Mother,</hi> and betray the Native Interests of their <hi>Countrey,</hi> to its most inveterate Enemies; not only holding a <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>respondence</hi> with them, but offering up <hi>Vows</hi> and <hi>Prayers</hi> for their <hi>Success,</hi> and discovering a cursed kind of laughter and satisfaction, at the losses, and misfortunes of their own <hi>Nation:</hi> an Indignity which no <hi>Government</hi> in the <hi>World,</hi> deserves <hi>less</hi> then <hi>this,</hi> and none upon <hi>Earth,</hi> would perhaps bear but <hi>this;</hi> but <hi>mercy</hi> is a <hi>God-like temper;</hi> and it would ill become this <hi>Place,</hi> to offer any thing against <hi>it:</hi> and I doubt not but <hi>Heaven</hi> it self will take care to avenge such <hi>monstrous</hi> Ingratitude▪</p>
            <p>I COULD farther shew you, with what <hi>Wisdom</hi> He unites and keeps together the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates,</hi> against the Disturber of the <hi>Peace</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:152267:27"/> of <hi>Christendom,</hi> for which, we are (next aster our Deliverance it self) as much beholding to <hi>Him,</hi> as for any one thing whatsoever. For by this means, the <hi>War</hi> is kept at a distance, and we live free from all Disturbance; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which, what could <hi>England</hi> hope for, but to be a Field of Blood.</p>
            <p>IT had long since been so, had not His <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty</hi> Interposed, we were ready to sheath our swords in one anothers bowels, while a <hi>Third</hi> Party (under the pretence of Assisting <hi>one</hi>) was gaping for an opportunity to devour <hi>both.</hi> Nay it had been so, notwithstanding this Interpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, were not the <hi>Enemy</hi> kept at a distance, by continuing <hi>Flanders</hi> the Seat of the <hi>War,</hi> and (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter all our noise) all that's done to support our <hi>Allies,</hi> is no less than necessary to support our <hi>selves;</hi> It's to find the Enemy work, on that <hi>side,</hi> that we may live in quiet at <hi>home;</hi> No com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <hi>Blessing,</hi> if we consider what our <hi>Neighbours</hi> both in <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> and elsewhere, suffer by the scourge of <hi>War.</hi> And notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the malicious and unreasonable <hi>sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gestions</hi> of some, who cry out (tho' with no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>design</hi> than to foment our <hi>Animosities</hi> and <hi>Divisions</hi>) that we are at the vast Expence of a <hi>needless War,</hi> to maintain the Dominions of a Foreign <hi>Prince:</hi> Yet all men of <hi>sense</hi> know,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:152267:27"/> that the preservation of <hi>Flanders</hi> is as much, nay more, for the Interest of <hi>England,</hi> than of <hi>Spain;</hi> If that should once fall a <hi>Victim</hi> to <hi>France,</hi> we need not sure, be told at this time of day, what would soon follow.</p>
            <p>AND therefore, since we have no other <hi>Choice</hi> then to fight for <hi>Flanders,</hi> or for <hi>England,</hi> in <hi>Flanders,</hi> or in <hi>England;</hi> there's none but men <hi>besides</hi> themselves, or otherwise notoriously <hi>Byast,</hi> that would chuse the later.</p>
            <p>BUT I need insist no longer upon this. It's but too <hi>plain,</hi> we ought to value and admire <hi>Him</hi> for his own sake; let us now see what obligations lie upon <hi>us,</hi> to do it for our <hi>Own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND▪ what can in this Case, be less expected from a <hi>Grateful</hi> and a <hi>Brave People,</hi> to so <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous;</hi> so <hi>Deserving</hi> a <hi>Prince?</hi> But that we contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute our endeavours, that we may neither be wanting to our selves, nor in <hi>Duty,</hi> and <hi>Affection,</hi> to <hi>Him,</hi> but that we share in His <hi>dangers,</hi> and promote His <hi>Designs,</hi> and do all, that in every one of us lies, to keep <hi>Him</hi> in a Capacity, of meeting His Enemies with equal Numbers; whom they dare never <hi>attack</hi> but with unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable <hi>odds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THIS Indeed, is but what we owe to our <hi>selves,</hi> to our <hi>Countrey,</hi> our <hi>Families,</hi> our <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity,</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:152267:28"/> and beyond all, to our Religion; for all these are at <hi>Stake,</hi> and they are (let some pretend what they will) the very things we contend for in the present <hi>War</hi> with <hi>France;</hi> which is endeavouring to get not only our <hi>Houses,</hi> but the <hi>Houses</hi> of <hi>God</hi> into their possessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and how they will use both them and us, they have given us more than a <hi>Specimen</hi> by what they have done at <hi>home,</hi> in their own Countrey: Where within these few Years, there were more than a Thousand places of <hi>Gods</hi> pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>Worship,</hi> where some Hundred Thousands of <hi>Protestants</hi> served <hi>God</hi> Religiously and Truly; and yet the <hi>French,</hi> at least the <hi>Popish</hi> Fury, hath turn'd all those Churches into ruinous Heaps, and treated the poor <hi>Owners</hi> of them (tho' their <hi>Countrey-men,</hi> their <hi>Neighbours,</hi> their <hi>Friends</hi> and <hi>Relations</hi>) with more Scorn and Contempt, more Barbarity and Cruelty, than has been heard among <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Infidels.</hi> So that it's every Mans <hi>Interest,</hi> to ingage in this quarrel; and were it not only so, yet a due sense of <hi>Honour</hi> might excite all Persons of <hi>Character</hi> and <hi>Reputation,</hi> to follow the Example of their <hi>KING,</hi> who hath so often exposed himself for us, and who is still ready to sacrifice his Life for our safety.</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:152267:28"/>
            <p>I AM sure, there's no man can tell me, what it was for (almost this Age past) we desired more than such a <hi>King;</hi> what it was we long'd for more, than a <hi>Prince</hi> without any private <hi>designs,</hi> and beyond all <hi>suspicion, Firm,</hi> in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions <hi>Interest</hi> and <hi>Quarrel</hi> against <hi>France;</hi> this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry qualification had atton'd for all other failings, and the want of it (for ought I know) hath been, in a great Measure, the <hi>source</hi> of all our Miscar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riages; and not only Mischievous to us, but Fatal to all <hi>Europe.</hi> And now that, <hi>that God,</hi> who brings Good out of Evil; hath as it were, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully compli'd with our desires, and blest us with a <hi>Prince,</hi> who (besides His other endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments) is of all <hi>other</hi> the best qualified this way. A <hi>Prince</hi> whom that <hi>Monarch</hi> always fear'd, and has now more reason to fear than ever. Shall we not lay hold of the opportunity, and push on the present <hi>War,</hi> with the utmost Vigor.</p>
            <p>BELIEVE it, to talk or think of restoring the late <hi>King,</hi> without a <hi>French Army</hi> (as some of our Disaffected Scriblers would seem to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose upon us) or to think that such an <hi>Army,</hi> if they could restore Him, would then only take their leave and be gone (as others of them would perswade us) is a <hi>Vanity,</hi> a <hi>Madness,</hi> that may require our <hi>Pity,</hi> but seems to be past our <hi>Cure.</hi> And therefore, to <hi>Cabal</hi> or <hi>Plot,</hi> or <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure</hi>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:152267:29"/> or <hi>Murmur,</hi> or if we arrive not to this height of Undutifulness and Folly, but only remain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concern'd, or stand only <hi>Gazeing</hi> and looking on, as if it were no great matter how the War succeeded; must needs be, because we will not exercise so much <hi>Fore-thought,</hi> as to consider the Dreadful <hi>Consequences</hi> of miscarrying in it.</p>
            <p>ALL wise Men will tell you, we had better be subdued by any Nation under Heaven than the <hi>French,</hi> for besides, that no <hi>other,</hi> considering our Situation (as one hath lately observ'd) hath <hi>Naval Forces</hi> enough to secure such a <hi>Conquest;</hi> so no <hi>other</hi> would insult and inslave us at the rate they would. If the <hi>Turk</hi> should subdue us, he would (saith the same Author) miserably <hi>Tyrannize,</hi> but yet for a small Yearly <hi>Tribute,</hi> he would allow us the <hi>exercise</hi> of our <hi>Religion.</hi> If other <hi>Nations,</hi> either their <hi>Distance</hi> would slack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en our <hi>Bonds,</hi> or their <hi>weakness,</hi> would press us more <hi>lightly:</hi> But <hi>France</hi> is our next <hi>Neighbour,</hi> very powerful by Sea and Land, able to load us with heavy <hi>Chains,</hi> and to rivet them up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us: <hi>Besides,</hi> she has found us capable of being a <hi>Rival</hi> to her <hi>Glory,</hi> and we know, who it is, at this minute, that stops her <hi>Conquests,</hi> who gives <hi>Check,</hi> to all her aspiring <hi>Designs:</hi> Nay she has felt the Power of our <hi>Arms</hi> in her
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152267:29"/>
               <hi>Bowels,</hi> and has been <note n="*" place="margin">This Conquest was undertaken upon just grounds, <hi>Edward</hi> II. King of <hi>England▪</hi> having Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried <hi>Isabella</hi> Daughter to <hi>Philip the Fair</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> whose three Sons dying without Issue, the Crown descended to the Heirs of <hi>Isabella;</hi> and then it was, when <hi>Edw.</hi> III. in right of his Mother claimed the Kingdom of <hi>France,</hi> that they made their <hi>Salique Law,</hi> which could however, bar only for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and not for the time past; and therefore the King invaded <hi>France,</hi> and was very successful in all the Battels he fought, but by reason of several diversions at home, this Success was not pursued by his immediate Successors; yet <hi>Hen.</hi> V. coming to the Crown (A <hi>Prince</hi> of a Warlike temper) and considering, that, not only <hi>Normandy, Guien, Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> and <hi>Anjou,</hi> were the rightful <hi>Inheritances</hi> of the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> but also his just Title to the <hi>Whole Kingdom,</hi> derived from <hi>Isabella</hi> aforesaid; after he had first by <hi>Ambassadors</hi> set forth, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded his Right, he with an <hi>English Army</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vades <hi>France,</hi> and after he had won several Battles, was at last Married to <hi>Katharine,</hi> Daughter of <hi>Charles</hi> VI. And thereupon Declared and Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>King</hi> of <hi>France</hi> in Reversion: <hi>Charles</hi> and <hi>Isabel</hi> his Queen to Reign during their Lives, and <hi>Isabel</hi> surviving <hi>Charles, at</hi> her death, made a <hi>Will,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring her Son in Law, <hi>Henry</hi> V. Heir to all her Goods, and to the <hi>Crown▪</hi> which gives the <hi>Kings</hi> of <hi>England</hi> a farther Right to the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>France:</hi> And I am perswaded if the <hi>French King</hi> had half so much right to <hi>England,</hi> as the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England</hi> hath to <hi>France,</hi> we should be pestered with his <hi>Manifesto's</hi> and <hi>Scribles,</hi> alledging his just Pretensions; as he calls all, that he makes.</note> Conquered by us, and has had such proofs of the <hi>English</hi> Valour, that she would be <hi>sure</hi> to take care never more▪ to stand in fear of her <hi>Antient Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies:</hi> And upon these grounds we are to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect no <hi>Mercy</hi> at her <hi>Hands,</hi> but the worst of an <hi>Hostile Fury;</hi> and nothing perhaps, <hi>less</hi> than our total <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>version,</hi> would serve their turn. Nay, when we consider, how bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barbarously they use the <hi>People</hi> whom they <hi>Subdue,</hi> tho' of their own <hi>Religion,</hi> without regard to <hi>Churches</hi> or <hi>Religious</hi> Houses, or the very <hi>Sepulchers</hi> of the <hi>Dead,</hi> tho' <hi>Princes</hi> themselves; we may believe, our <hi>English Papists</hi> (however they may flatter themselves) would meet with no better <hi>Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> than others: But for those <hi>Protestants,</hi> who, tho' at ease in their <hi>Fortunes,</hi> and injoying all
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:152267:30"/> the Priviledges of their Fellow Subjects, are yet <hi>Restless</hi> and <hi>Dissatisfied,</hi> and <hi>Weary</hi> of a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, that's the only <hi>Security</hi> of their <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> and <hi>Estates;</hi> Surely, as they will be the easiest, so they will be the most despised <hi>Prey</hi> of their <hi>Enemy,</hi> who (if they have any <hi>Man▪hood,</hi> or any thing that's <hi>great</hi> in them; will shew more <hi>Favour</hi> to the brave <hi>Defenders</hi> of their <hi>Countrey,</hi> than to those, who have so basely, and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherously deserted and betrayed it.</p>
            <p>BUT I know, if I should Discourse at this <hi>rate,</hi> out of this <hi>place,</hi> or where I might expect an answer, I should presently be told; that I had used a great many <hi>words</hi> to little purpose, and had run on all along upon a false <hi>ground,</hi> for that the Great King of <hi>France,</hi> hath nothing of <hi>Self,</hi> in all this, nor is he farther concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, then out of a Principle of <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerosity</hi> to Espouse an <hi>Oppressed,</hi> and to restore, an <hi>Exil'd Prince, That he</hi> was neither opprest, nor banished, is plain enough: And on whose <hi>side</hi> the <hi>Oppression</hi> lay, we all know; and yet we will allow them, that, that <hi>Monarch,</hi> may seemingly with much Gallantry, Espouse His <hi>Cause</hi> till he see a fair opportunity of setting up his <hi>Own:</hi> but, to be sure, no longer. <hi>Or</hi> sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose he should not do <hi>this:</hi> can we however think, that he would not demand so great
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:152267:30"/> a <hi>Charge,</hi> as that the whole <hi>Wealth</hi> of the <hi>Nation</hi> would be too little to answer? and were it not better <hi>Policy</hi> in us (tho we had no other induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) to supply <hi>Him,</hi> even to a <hi>Moiety</hi> of what we <hi>have;</hi> who will preserve the <hi>rest,</hi> by keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing such Enemies <hi>out,</hi> and by cherishing and protecting us in our <hi>Religion,</hi> and other <hi>Rights.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To be sparing in a case of such <hi>Necessity,</hi> is to be <hi>Wanting,</hi> and indeed <hi>Cruel,</hi> to our selves, and our Posterity: like the fatal <hi>Parsimony</hi> of the <hi>People</hi> of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> who refused to supply their own <hi>Emperour</hi> (tho' by way of <hi>Loan</hi>) with a thirti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth part of that <hi>Money,</hi> which the <hi>Turkish Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour</hi> deprived them of, together with the lives of the wealthiest of them. Whereas, by that sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable <hi>Supply,</hi> they might in all likelihood; have preserved their <hi>City</hi> and their <hi>Lives</hi> too.</p>
            <p>'TWERE easie to shew, what a poor thing <hi>Money</hi> is, in respect of our <hi>Religion,</hi> our <hi>Lives,</hi> our <hi>Laws,</hi> and our <hi>Liberties;</hi> and it's not yet <hi>Seven Years,</hi> since all considerate <hi>Men</hi> and good <hi>Protestants</hi> amongst us, would have given more than this <hi>War</hi> will cost us, to have been under the <hi>Circumstances</hi> we now are: But (God be thanked) there's no need to insist upon this. Those worthy <hi>Patriots</hi> who so freely and cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully find out <hi>Ways</hi> and <hi>Means</hi> to support the <hi>War,</hi> are highly sensible of <hi>it.</hi> And all I have to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:152267:31"/>
               <hi>offer</hi> upon their accounts, is; to <hi>pray</hi> as <hi>David,</hi> when the <hi>People</hi> even beyond what he expected, offer'd so <hi>willingly</hi> towards a Publick <hi>Good. O</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Chron. 29. 18.</note>
               <hi>Lord God of Abraham, of Isaac, and of Israel our Fathers, keep this for ever, in the imagination of the thoughts of the heart of thy people.</hi> But to return, <hi>That</hi> I may leave nothing unsaid, to open the Eyes of those who are not <hi>wilfully</hi> Blind; I will for their satisfaction, <hi>suppose;</hi> that this extravagantly ambitious <hi>King</hi> (upon whom they so much <hi>depend</hi>) had no private <hi>design,</hi> but would only cleer the <hi>Way</hi> to the <hi>Throne,</hi> and then fairly draw off, without any other <hi>Consideration</hi> than the satisfaction of his own <hi>Haughty</hi> and <hi>Ambitious Humour:</hi> Let us I say suppose this (tho' indeed it's next to impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) yet even in this <hi>Case;</hi> Might not the <hi>Prince</hi> whom he left repossest (I only pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sume to ask the Question) justly write himself; <hi>James the Conquerour?</hi> And tho' I am not to determine, how mercifuly he might use us, if left to his own <hi>Conduct</hi> (tho' we must believe him more than a Saint to forget, what is past) yet, considering <hi>how</hi> he has been influenced; and (considering his Principles) how he still must <hi>be:</hi> (if ever <hi>Divine Judgment</hi>) as a pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nishment for our <hi>Sins,</hi> should suffer this to come to <hi>pass;</hi> The very thoughts of what
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:152267:31"/> we might expect, are so full of <hi>Horror,</hi> that I chuse rather to draw a <hi>Vail</hi> over it, and pass it in <hi>silence,</hi> than go about to display it; and if any Man be so <hi>Weak,</hi> or so <hi>Short sighted,</hi> as to wish or desire it, I am perswaded, that a short change with a Subject of <hi>France,</hi> would very effectually <hi>Cure</hi> him of his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lady</hi> and <hi>Folly</hi> too.</p>
            <p>And yet <hi>Our Case</hi> might be, much more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperate than some of <hi>Theirs,</hi> and no <hi>better,</hi> to be <hi>sure,</hi> than that of the Protestant Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects under that <hi>Crown;</hi> and how it should be <hi>worse,</hi> is not <hi>easie</hi> to imagine. And now,</p>
            <p>SINCE, those very Men amongst us, who seem most fond of the late <hi>Kings return,</hi> do yet pretend, they would by no means have <hi>Him</hi> come with a <hi>French Power; as</hi> being aware of the dreadful <hi>Consequences</hi> thereof. <hi>Since</hi> it is not possible he should come by any other, or any other way. The a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bused Affections, of his <hi>Quondam Subjects</hi> (except a few not worth the naming) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now settled upon a <hi>Prince,</hi> who has gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them with the Hazard of His <hi>Life.</hi> A <hi>Prince,</hi> that is not only <hi>flesh,</hi> of our <hi>flesh;</hi> and <hi>bone,</hi> of our <hi>bone;</hi> and so our <hi>Natural Liege Lord;</hi> but of our <hi>Religion</hi> also, and therefore the <hi>dearer</hi> to <hi>us,</hi> as we are the safer; this being <hi>so,</hi> it is not possible they should think of <hi>recalling</hi> a <hi>Prince</hi>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:152267:32"/> under whose <hi>Administration,</hi> they suffered so much, and whose incensed <hi>wrath,</hi> would not be easily appeased; and whose <hi>thirst,</hi> for <hi>Ʋnli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited Power,</hi> He would be sure to <hi>quench</hi> at our <hi>Cost;</hi> and therefore must come by a <hi>French Power,</hi> or not at <hi>all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SINCE, Such a <hi>Power,</hi> if they could set him on <hi>English ground</hi> (which I much questi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) would either, in his <hi>Name,</hi> and under his <hi>Ʋmbrage,</hi> do all for <hi>Themselves: or</hi> at their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>off,</hi> demand such <hi>vast Sums,</hi> as we could never pay; and <hi>yet</hi> for not paying, would be exposed to all the <hi>Miseries,</hi> that <hi>Scorn</hi> or <hi>Cruelty</hi> could invent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Since,</hi> After they had done <hi>this (or</hi> suppose they should not do it) <hi>They</hi> would at, <hi>best,</hi> leave us in the hands of a <hi>Conqueror,</hi> all <hi>Incensed,</hi> full of <hi>VVrath</hi> and <hi>Revenge;</hi> who used us <hi>not over well,</hi> when <hi>He</hi> had no pretence to that <hi>Title:</hi> but would now be sure (without usurping a Dispensing Power) make his <hi>Will</hi> our <hi>Law,</hi> and impose whatever his <hi>Ambition,</hi> his <hi>Wrath,</hi> or a Jesuiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal <hi>Cruelty</hi> could inflict.</p>
            <p>SINCE, Our <hi>Religion</hi> (with which nothing should come in Competition) is secured to <hi>us,</hi> and our <hi>posterity,</hi> being wrapt up and safe, not <hi>only</hi> in His <hi>Majesty</hi> (whom <hi>God</hi> long pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve) But in those <hi>Illustrious Heirs</hi> of the <hi>Crown, Her Royal Highness,</hi> and <hi>Her Royal Son;</hi> in <hi>whom</hi> we may one day be <hi>happy.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="63" facs="tcp:152267:32"/>
            <p>SINCE, Our <hi>Laws</hi> are once more <hi>Sacred,</hi> our <hi>Priviledges Allowed,</hi> our <hi>Rights,</hi> and <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties Cherished.</hi> And <hi>Since</hi> we are <hi>Blessed</hi> with a <hi>King</hi> by whose <hi>Prowess,</hi> and <hi>Conduct,</hi> by whose <hi>Justice,</hi> and <hi>Goodness,</hi> we may (if not wanting to our selves) be as <hi>Great,</hi> as <hi>Happy,</hi> and as <hi>Dreadful,</hi> as <hi>Ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>SINCE, <hi>This, I</hi> say, is <hi>so,</hi> it is not possible (unless we be in love with <hi>Chains</hi>) and fond to see our <hi>Religion</hi> truckle to <hi>Popery,</hi> our <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty</hi> to <hi>Slavery,</hi> our <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Priviledges,</hi> to <hi>Courtesie:</hi> unless we desire to see our <hi>Lives</hi> exposed, and our <hi>Estates,</hi> offered as an <hi>Obla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> to a superstious, greedy <hi>Church;</hi> or as a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> to the <hi>Soldier</hi> that shall destroy <hi>us:</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>less, I <hi>say,</hi> we are fond of these things, it is not possible we should <hi>desire,</hi> or ever <hi>long</hi> for such an <hi>Administration,</hi> as will certainly produce <hi>them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IF therefore, we have any Natural <hi>Love</hi> for our <hi>Countrey, or</hi> any Supernatural <hi>Affection,</hi> for our <hi>Religion, or</hi> any Natural <hi>Instinct</hi> of <hi>Self Preservation, or</hi> any Sense of <hi>Honour,</hi> in Acting suitably to such <hi>Principles;</hi> If a <hi>Royal Example,</hi> can <hi>incite us, or</hi> our own <hi>Welfare</hi> and <hi>Safety</hi> incourage us; <hi>Let us</hi> in the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> as we <hi>Value</hi> any, or all of these <hi>Dear Things,</hi> in all Due <hi>Thankfulness</hi> to the <hi>Authour,</hi> and in all Loyal Duty, and Affection, to the <hi>Instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:152267:33"/> of our <hi>Deliverance;</hi> turn from our <hi>Sins,</hi> and <hi>Ʋnite</hi> and <hi>Strengthen</hi> our Selves, against the <hi>Common Enemy,</hi> of our <hi>Religion,</hi> and <hi>Civil Rights,</hi> as the only <hi>way,</hi> to have our <hi>Peace,</hi> and <hi>Happiness,</hi> Restored and Settled, upon <hi>sure</hi> and <hi>lasting Foundations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AND <hi>this</hi> I conceive, is the best <hi>course</hi> we can take, to lessen this Great <hi>Loss;</hi> so, as it may not prove <hi>fatal</hi> to us: To <hi>Stand</hi> by our <hi>King,</hi> with our <hi>Lives</hi> and <hi>Fortunes:</hi> To <hi>Pray</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantly, and to <hi>Pray</hi> fervently, that <hi>God</hi> would Protect <hi>Him,</hi> from the private <hi>Machinations,</hi> and open <hi>Violence</hi> of His <hi>Enemies;</hi> that He would preserve <hi>Him,</hi> to perfect that <hi>Great,</hi> that <hi>Glorious Work,</hi> He hath so Generously, and so Successfully <hi>Begun,</hi> that so we may enjoy <hi>Him,</hi> in <hi>Peace,</hi> and esteem <hi>Him,</hi> as the <hi>Israelites</hi> did <hi>David, the light of our Israel;</hi> and as they did<note place="margin">2 Sam. 21.</note>
               <hi>Josiah, the breath of our Nostrils.</hi> The serious ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment<note place="margin">Lam. 4. 20.</note>
               <hi>whereof,</hi> will not suffer <hi>us</hi> to be wanting in all Duty and Affection to <hi>Him,</hi> whom <hi>God</hi> continue long over us; and let <hi>all</hi> that <hi>Love</hi> the <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Happiness,</hi> the <hi>Well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare</hi> and <hi>Glory,</hi> of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> say, <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now to God onely Wise, Father, Son, and Holy Ghost, be ascribed, as is Most Due, All Glory, Honour, Power, Praise, Might, Majesty, and Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, Now and for Ever, Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:152267:33"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>